Guide to the Robert Parmelee Wilder Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Robert Parmelee Wilder Papers
1840-1940
RG 38
Yale University Divinity School Library
10
(25 boxes)
Material documents the development of the Christian missionary movement among students in the United States and Europe, 1886-1938. Family correspondence documents the missionary work of Wilder's parents in India, 1846-1875, as well as his work in India, 1893-1902. Robert Parmelee Wilder was born in India of missionary parents in 1863. He earned the A.B. and A.M. degrees from Princeton University (1886, 1888) and the B.D. degree from UnionTheological Seminary (1891). He was a founder of the Student Volunteer Movement (1886), missionary in India (1893-1902), traveling secretary for Student Christian Movements in Europe (1903-1916), secretary of Religious Work Department, YMCA (1916-1919), General Secretary of the Student Volunteer Movement (1919-1927) and Executive Secretary of the Near East Christian Council (1927-1933). He died on March 27, 1938.
Wilder, Robert P., 1863-1938
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1863 Born in India of missionary parents: Royal Gould Wilder and Eliza Jane (Smith) Wilder
1886 A.B., Princeton University
1886 Instrumental in the founding of the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions at Mt. Hermon Conference
1886-1887 Travel to colleges and universities throughout the U.S. on behalf of the Student Volunteer Movement
1888 A.M., Princeton University
1891 B.D., Union Theological Seminary
1891-1892 Travel in Europe; instrumental in founding of British Student Volunteer Missionary Union
1892 Married to Helene Sophie Olsson who became mother of his four daughters: Ruth, Grace, Elizabeth and Dorothy
1893-1897 Work in India as secretary of the college department of the Y.M.C.A.
1897-1899 In the U.S.
1899-1902 General Secretary of the Indian National Council of Y.M.C.A.'s. Forced to return from India due to ill health
1903-1904 Traveling secretary for Student Christian Movement of Norway, Sweden, Denmark and Finland
1905-1916 Work with the Student Christian Movement of Great Britain and Ireland as Traveling Secretary, London Secretary and Evangelistic Secretary. During this period Wilder also worked for the World Student Christian Federation, speaking at universities throughout continental Europe.
1916-1919 Senior Secretary of Religious Work Department of International Committee of Y.M.C.A. (in U.S.A.)
1919-1927 General Secretary of Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions
1927-1933 Executive Secretary of Near East Christian Council
1934-1935 Spoke at conferences for the Intervarsity Fellowship of Evangelical Unions in Great Britain
1938 Mar 27 Died
Biographical information taken from Who Was Who in America, Vol. 1, 1897-1942
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence
II. Notebooks and Diaries
III. Writings
IV. Printed Material
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia
The majority of the letters are addressed to Wilder; they are primarily in manuscript form and several European languages are represented. Correspondence with John R. Mott was not included in the chronological sequence of the general correspondence because of the bulk and substance of these letters. The letters in the general section and those exchanged with John R. Mott are a valuable source of documentation for the researcher interested in the development of the missionary movement among students. Wilder was intimately involved in student missionary movements in the United States and Europe from their conception in the late nineteenth century through to the dissensions which arose between conservative and liberal elements in the movements in the 1920's and 1930's. The development of the Student Volunteer Movement in the United States can be traced from Wilder's first trip to colleges and universities in 1887 to his tenure as General Secretary of the Movement and in extensive correspondence with Jesse R. Wilson, his successor as General Secretary. The student missionary movement in Great Britain between 1905 and 1916 is documented by substantive correspondence reporting statistics and events. Outside of the field of student missionary work, Wilder's role in the development of the Near East Christian Council is documented in his correspondence from 1927 to 1933. Earlier letters from John N. Forman give informative accounts of missionary work in India, dealing with matters of method and policy.
The Family Correspondence in this collection is not extensive but does provide valuable insight into the early mission work of Wilder's parents in India. The elder Wilders sailed for India in 1846 as missionaries under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. In 1852 they founded the Kolhapur (or Kolapoor) Mission where they engaged in educational work later independently and under the Presbyterian Board until 1875.
The notebooks and diaries of Series II date from 1880 to 1938. All were written by Wilder except two small volumes belonging to his mother and one written by John N. Forman, Wilder's colleague in Student Volunteer Movement work and a missionary in India. Entries in Wilder's diaries are somewhat sporadic and include descriptions of daily events and notes regarding discussions and meetings. Notebooks from Wilder's student days include notes from addresses heard at the Northfield, Massachusetts summer school in 1888, as well as class notes.
The writings of Series III are divided into three sections:
A. Addresses, Bible study notes (1882-1935, n.d.)
B. Published writings (1890-1935, n.d.)
C. Reports, report letters (1888-1933, n.d.)
A major portion of Wilder's time was spent in speaking to audiences on various aspects of the Christian life. Wilder's addresses and notes for discussions are arranged topically with subjects ranging from prayer to work in India to the student missionary movement. Wilder's published writings covered many of the same subject areas and appeared in various European languages. The reports section of Series II provides an informative outline of Wilder's activities in association with the various organizations which he served.
The printed material in Series IV is also divided into three sections:
A. Reviews of Wilder's publications (1899-1937, n.d.)
B. Material related to the various organizations served by Wilder (1840-1937, n.d.)
C. Miscellaneous
Series V, Personal Items and Memorabilia includes:
A. Genealogical material (1878-1926, n.d.) which documents Wilder's claim as a Mayflower descendant.
B. Material related to Wilder's parents and sister (1840-1929, n.d.), including an interesting series of communications between Royal G. Wilder and government officials in India regarding a property dispute.
C. Biographical material regarding Wilder (1887-1940, n.d.) including clippings and articles, publicity notices, and material gathered by Ruth Wilder Braisted in her preparations for writing a biography of her father.
D. Photographs (1879-192S, n.d.), primarily of Wilder and family members.
E. Miscellaneous personal items, including material such as Wilder's Bible and the notice of his engagement.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Notebooks and Diaries
III. Writings
IV. Printed Material
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia
College students in missionary work; College students -- Religious life; Missions -- India; Missions; Missionaries; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963; Forman, John N., -1967; Fries, Karl, 1861-1943; Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1884-1968; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Porter, David R. (David Richard), 1882-1973; Speer, Robert E. (Robert Elliott), 1867-1947; Tatlow, Tissington, 1876-1957; Wilder, Grace; Wilder, Robert P., 1863-1938; Wilder, Royal Gould, 1816-1887; Zwemer, Samuel Marinus, 1867-1952; Near East Christian Council; Student Christian Movement (Great Britain); Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions
- Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  A. General correspondence is arranged chronologically with notable correspondents indicated on the folder headings. One folder of undated and fragmentary correspondence follows the dated material.
  B. Correspondence with John R. Mott is arranged chronologically.
  Correspondence of John R. Mott located in the General Correspondence section consists only of copies of letters sent to Wilder by other correspondents.
  C. Family correspondence is arranged by family members:
  Royal G. and Eliza Jane Wilder (parents)
  Grace Wilder (sister)
  William Wilder (brother)
  Helene Wilder (wife)
  Ruth, Grace, Elizabeth and Dorothy Wilder (daughters)
  Other family members.
  The material is arranged chronologically within each of these sections.
  Frequent or notable correspondents include:
  Barbour, George,
  Beach, Harlan P.,
  Black, Howard,
  Braisted, Paul,
  Brown, Arthur Judson,
  Forman, John N.,
  Fraser, Donald,
  Fries, Karl,
  Frost, Henry W.,
  Hallesby, Ole,
  Henriod, Henry-Louis,
  Holden, J. Stuart,
  Johnson, Douglas,
  Latourette, Kenneth Scott,
  McBrier, Edwin M.,
  McCosh, James,
  McCulloch, William P.,
  Mackie, Robert C.,
  MacMillan, Hugh,
  Miller, Francis,
  Miller, Wlliam McE.,
  Moltke, Count Joakim,
  Moody, Dwight L.
  Moorhead, Max Wood
  Mott, John R.
  Nicol, James H.
  Nicolay, Baron Paul
  Ober, Charles K.
  Oldham, Joseph H.
  Paton, William
  Pelly, Richard Lawrence
  Phildius, Eberhard
  Pierson, Delavan
  Porteous, Robert W.
  Porter, David R.
  Reid, David
  Rose, William
  Rutgers, H.C.
  Seton, Walter
  - Chronologically arranged correspondence
    - Various, 1878-1880 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Various, 1881-1885 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Incl. from: William P. Taylor; C.K. Ober; Luther D. Wishard, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Incl. from: John Forman; L.D. Wishard; C.K. Ober; Henry Clay Trumbull, 1887 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Incl from: J. Forman; L.D. Wishard; Robert Speer, 1887 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Incl. from: Samuel M. Zwemer; J. Forman; R. Speer, 1888 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Incl. from: S. Zwemer; R. Speer, 1888 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Incl. from: J. Hudson Taylor; S. Zwemer; R. Speer, 1888 Aug-Sep (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Various, 1888 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Incl. from: J. Forman; L. Wishard, R. Speer, 1889 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Incl. from: Karl Fries, 1889 May-Jul (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Incl. from: J. Forman; K. Fries; R. Speer, 1889 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Incl. from: R. Speer, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Incl. from: William G.T. Shedd; Dwight L. Moody; James McCosh, 1891 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Incl. from: L. Wishard; J. Moltke, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Incl. from: L. Wishard, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Incl. from: S. Zwemer; J. Moltke, 1894-1895 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Incl. from: J.N. Farquhar, 1896-1897 Feb (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Incl. to/from: R. Speer, 1897 Mar-1898 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Incl. from: H.N. Luce G.S. Eddy R. Speer, 1899 Jan-Jul (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Incl. from: R. Speer, 1899 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Incl. from: G.S. Eddy R. Speer, 1900 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Incl. from: G.S. Eddy, 1900 Apr-May (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Incl. from: G.S. Eddy; J. Moltke; R. Speer, 1900 Jun-Aug (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Various, 1900 Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Incl. from: R.A. Hume, 1901 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Incl. from: G.S. Eddy, 1901 Apr-May (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Incl. from: John R. Mott; G.S. Eddy, 1901 Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Incl. from: G.S. Eddy J.R. Mott; K. Fries; J. Moltke; Paul Nicolay, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries; J. Moltke; P. Nicolay; Tissington Tatlow, 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Incl. from: P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1905 Jan-Sep (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Incl. from: P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1905 Oct-Dec (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Incl. from: J.R. Mott; Robert E. Speer; Karl Fries; J. Moltke; P. Nicolay, 1906 Jan-Mar (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Incl to/from: T. Tatlow, 1906 Apr-Dec (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Incl. from: T. Tatlow, 1907 Jan-Jun (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1907 Aug-Dec (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries; T. Tatlow, 1908 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Incl. from: P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Mott; P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Incl. to/from: Wm. W. Borden; J.R. Mott; K. Fries; R. Speer; T. Tatlow, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Mott; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1912 Jan-Jul (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Mott; Wm. W. Borden; K. Fries; P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1912 Aug-Dec (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Incl. to: P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1913 Jan-Aug (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Incl. to/from: G.S. Eddy; T. Tatlow, 1913 Sep-Dec (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Various, 1914 Jan-Mar (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Mott; T. Tatlow, 1914 Apr-May (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries, 1914 Jun-Jul (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1914 Aug-Dec (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Mott; T. Tatlow, 1915 Jan-May (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Incl. to/from: T. Tatlow, 1915 Jun-Dec (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Incl. to/from: G.S. Eddy; K. Fries; J. Moltke; P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1916 Jan-Apr (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Incl. to/from: P. Nicolay; T. Tatlow, 1916 May-Jun (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Incl. from: P. Nicolay, 1916 Jul-Dec (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Incl. to/from: P. Nicolay, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Incl. to/from: P. Nicolay, 1918 Jan-Aug (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries; P. Nicolay, 1918 Sep-Dec (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Incl. from: P. Nicolay, 1919 Jan-Apr (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Incl. from: David R. Porter; J.R. Mott; P. Nicolay, 1919 May-Aug (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Incl. to/from: J. Moltke; J.R. Mott; T. Tatlow, 1919 Sep-Dec (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Incl. to/from: S. Zwemer; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1920 Jan-Jun (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Incl. to/from: J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1920 Jul-Dec (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Incl. to/from: J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Various, 1922 Jan-Jul (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Incl. from: J. Moltke, 1922 Aug-Dec (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Incl. to/from: S.W. Zwemer; Pierre Maury; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Incl. to/from: Kenneth Scott Latourette; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1924 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Incl. to/from: Arthur Judson Brown; J. Moltke; T. Tatlow, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Incl. to/from: Jesse R. Wilson; J. Moltke; R. Speer, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Incl. to/from: Jesse R. Wilson; R. Speer, 1927 Jan-Jun (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Incl. to/from: K.S. Latourette; J.R. Wilson, 1927 Jul-Sep (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Incl. to/from: Arthur Judson Brown; J.R. Wilson, 1927 Oct-Dec (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Incl. from: J.R. Wilson, 1928 Jan-Mar (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson; J. Moltke, 1928 Apr-Sep (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson J. Moltke, 1928 Oct-Dec (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Various, 1929 Jan-Jun (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson, 1929 Jul-Dec (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Incl. from: Charles T. Studd; J.R. Wilson; T. Tatlow, 1930 Jan-May (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Incl. to: J.R. Wilson, 1930 Jun-Dec (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Various, 1931 Jan-Jun (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Incl. from: K. Fries, 1931 Jul-Dec (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Various, 1932 Jan-Mar (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Incl. to: K.S. Latourette; J.R. Wilson, 1932 Apr-Oct (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Incl. from: K.S. Latourette; S. Zwemer; R. Speer, 1932 Nov-Dec (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Incl. to/from: S. Zwemer; J.R. Wilson; K. Fries; J. Moltke; R. Speer, 1933 Jan-Mar (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson; K. Fries; T. Tatlow, 1933 Apr-Jun (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson; K. Fries; J. Moltke, 1933 Jul-Aug (Box 8, Folder 86)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson, 1933 Sep-Dec (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Incl. to: J.R. Wilson, 1934 Jan-Feb (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Various, 1934 Mar-Apr (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Incl. from: J.R. Wilson, 1934 May-Jun (Box 9, Folder 90)
    - Incl. from: J.R. Wilson, 1934 Jul-Oct (Box 9, Folder 91)
    - Incl. to/from: T. Tatlow, 1934 Nov-Dec (Box 9, Folder 92)
    - Various, 1935 Jan-Apr (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Incl. to/from: J.R. Wilson; K. Fries, 1935 May-Dec (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Incl. from: J.R. Wilson, 1936 (Box 9, Folder 95)
    - Various, 1937-1938 Feb (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Letters of sympathy following Wilder's death, 1938 Mar (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Letters of sympathy following Wilder's death, 1938 Apr (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Letters of sympathy following Wilder's death, 1938 May-Dec (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Fragments and undated (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - Correspondence regarding personnel on SVM staff (To be consulted only with permission of librarian), 1924-1926, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - Correspondence with John R. Mott
    - Letters to/from Mott, 1886-1920 (Box 10, Folder 102-115)
    - Letters to/from Mott, 1921-1937, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 116-124)
  - Correspondence: Family
    - To/from R.G. and E.J. Wilder (parents), 1841-1846 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - To/from R.G. and E.J. Wilder (parents), 1847-1864 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - To/from R.G. and E.J. Wilder (parents), 1876-1888 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - To/from R.G. and E.J. Wilder (parents), 1889-1891 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - To/from R.G. and E.J. Wilder (parents), 1893-1899, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - To/from G. Wilder (sister), 1878-1888 (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - To/from G. Wilder (sister), 1889-1910, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - To/from W. Wilder (brother), 1880- 1920 (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - To/from W. Wilder (brother), 1921-1925 (Box 12, Folder 133)
    - To/from H. Wilder (wife), 1899- 1936, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - To/from daughters, 1918-1938 (Box 12, Folder 135)
    - To/from other family members, 1881-1926, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 136)
- Notebooks and Diaries, Series II
  The notebooks and diaries of Wilder are arranged chronologically. They are followed by one folder containing diaries of Eliza Jane Wilder and John N. Forman.
  - Diaries of Robert Wilder
    - R.P. Wilder, 1880-1888 (Box 13, Folder 137)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1889-1890 (Box 13, Folder 138)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1891-1892 (Box 13, Folder 139)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1893 (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1893-1894 (Box 13, Folder 141)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1895-1896 (Box 13, Folder 142)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1897-1898 (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1899-1906 (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1905 (Box 14, Folder 145)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1906-1907 (Box 14, Folder 146)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1908- 1909 (Box 14, Folder 147)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1910-1916 (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1911-1915 (Box 15, Folder 149)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1916-1922 (Box 15, Folder 150)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1923-1928 (Box 15, Folder 151)
    - R.P. Wilder, 1928-1938 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Diaries of others
    - Eliza Jane (Smith) Wilder; John N. Forman, 1916 (Box 15, Folder 153)
- Writings, Series III
  A. Addresses, Bible study notes are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  B. Published writings are arranged chronologically.
  C. Reports, report letters are arranged chronologically.
  - Addresses, Bible Study Notes
    - re: Evangelism, personal work, 1914- 1931, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 154)
    - re: Faith/doubt, 1909-1932 (Box 16, Folder 155)
    - re: Faith/doubt, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 156)
    - re: India, 1909, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 157)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects, 1882-1935 (Box 16, Folder 158)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 159)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 160)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects/Fragments, outlines, 1893-1929, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 161)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects/Fragments, outlines, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 162)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects/in Norwegian, 1908-1935, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 163)
    - re: Miscellaneous subjects/in Norwegian, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 164)
    - re: Missions, 1886-1935 (Box 17, Folder 165)
    - re: Missions, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 166)
    - re: Missions, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 167)
    - re: Near East Christian Council, 1929-1933, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 168)
    - re: Prayer/guidance, 1894-1936 (Box 17, Folder 169)
    - re: Prayer/guidance, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 170)
    - re: Spiritual regeneration and growth, 1890-1933 (Box 17, Folder 171)
    - re: Spiritual regeneration and growth (Box 17, Folder 172)
    - re: Spiritual regeneration and growth (Box 18, Folder 173)
    - re: Students/Student Volunteer Mvt., 1906-1926 (Box 18, Folder 174)
    - re: Students/Student Volunteer Mvt., n.d. (Box 18, Folder 175)
    - re: Students/Student Volunteer Mvt., n.d. (Box 18, Folder 176)
    - Notes on index cards on a variety of topics, No date (Box 26)
  - Published Writings
    - Various, 1890-1835, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 177-182)
  - Reports, report letters
    - Of Wilder, 1888-1933, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 183-196)
- Printed Material, Series IV
  A. Reviews of Wilder's books are arranged chronologically.
  B. Material related to organizations served by Wilder is arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization.
  C. Miscellaneous: one folder of material.
  - Reviews of Wilder's books
    - Various, 1899-1937, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 197)
  - Material related to organizations served by Wilder
    - Council of North American Student Movements, 1920-1921 (Box 21, Folder 198)
    - European Student Relief, 1921-1923 (Box 21, Folder 199)
    - Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America, 1919 (Box 21, Folder 200)
    - Indian National Council of Y.M.C.A.'s, 1899-1901 (Box 21, Folder 201)
    - Indian National Council of Y.M.C.A.'s, 1902-1903, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 202)
    - Intervarsity Fellowship of Evangelical Unions, 1928-1935, n.d. (Box 21, Folder 203)
    - Near East Christian Council, 1926-1937 (Box 21, Folder 204)
    - Student Christian Movement of Great Britain and Ireland (incl. Student Volunteer Mission ary Union), 1888-1934, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 205)
    - Student Volunteer Movements in Europe, 1892-1904, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 206)
    - Student Volunteer Movement in India, 1898,1901, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 207)
    - Student Volunteer Movement in U.S.A., 1886- 1933 (Box 22, Folder 208)
    - Student Volunteer Movement in U.S.A., n.d. (Box 22, Folder 209)
    - World's Student Christian Federation, 1888- 1921 (Box 22, Folder 210)
    - World's Student Christian Federation, 1922-1930 (Box 22, Folder 211)
    - World's Student Christian Federation, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 212)
    - World's Young Women's Christian Association, 1931, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 213)
    - Young Men's Christian Association, 1899-1933, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 214)
  - Miscellaneous printed material
    - Various (Box 23, Folder 215)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series V
  A. Genealogical material: arranged chronologically.
  B. Material related to Wilder's parents and sister: arranged chronologically.
  C. Biographical material: each section arranged chronologically.
  1. Clippings and articles.
  2. Publicity notices, itineraries.
  3. Material gathered by Ruth Wilder Braisted.
  D. Photographs: arranged chronologically.
  E. Miscellaneous personal items: arranged chronologically.
  - Genealogical material
    - Various, 1878 (Box 23, Folder 216)
    - Various, 1919-1926, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 217)
  - Material related to Wilder's parents and sister
    - Incl. Kolapoor Mission reports, 1840-1870 (Box 23, Folder 218)
    - Incl. regarding property dispute, Kolapoor Mission reports, 1871-l874 (Box 23, Folder 219)
    - Incl. regarding property dispute, Kolapoor Mission reports, l875-1877 (Box 23, Folder 220)
    - Various, 1883-1935, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 221-222)
  - Biographical Material
    - Clippings, articles, 1888- 1900 (Box 24, Folder 223)